Hey guys, welcome again. In this
particular session, we are going to talk
about TSCA CI/CD integration. So this
integration will allow you to run your
TSCA scripts in your own CI/CD pipeline
and it could be any particular CI/CD
integration tool like Genkins, GitLab or
any other tool. So from the later
versions of TSka like 15.2, two, TSka
has introduced a new CI/CD integration
uh client which is known as TSka
execution client. So you can basically
trigger your tests via this TSka
execution client which is only a command
line tool. So you can handle everything
through the command line. Right now this
option is only available with uh DEX
with AOS. Now we have already seen how
to set up Dex with AOS and run our test
events through uh a DEX agent, right? Um
now we'll try to do the same thing but
we'll try to run it through the
execution client rather than uh
triggering triggering it from the
workspace. We'll be triggering it from
the command
line. So uh let's get started. So first
uh we need to download the TSA execution
client. Now for this uh you can go to
Google and search for Tska execution
client and there you will find this
github.com tricentis tuska execution
client page. Okay. So this particular
TSA execution client is hosted on GitHub
with all the documentation and also the
actual client. Right? So if you go
through this uh page uh you will get the
client you can download it and then uh
it also provides you uh with a proper
description that it allows you to
trigger TSCA test events from CI/CD
pipelines or other environments. Okay,
it is an out ofbox solution. Okay, so
this you can run it from anywhere
basically, right? So you can run it from
a Linux system as well also as Windows
system. As I said, it is only supported
in TSA 15.2 two and above. So if you're
working in on the older versions, you
will not find this functionality. Okay.
The requirements system requirements are
pretty simple. Um you can run it in both
um both the systems either in Windows or
Linux. Okay. Uh in in Windows it is the
client is PowerShell script and in Linux
it is a shell script. So you can
download uh both the options if you are
working on a Windows or a Linux system.
Um the most important thing uh once you
download this is you need to set this
PowerShell execution policy. Okay, if
you're working on a Windows machine uh
we'll see how we can do that. For Linux
that is a separate configuration. So
that's the prerequisite and then to run
the TSA execution client uh we need to
execute this particular command. Okay.
So it is basically calling the
PowerShell script and then uh you need
to pass the TSA server URL the project
name um and then you can pass different
events. Okay, so you can execute
multiple test events or a single test
event on a Linux based system. This is
the command. So you just need to copy
and paste this command and then replace
this values like the TSA server URL, the
project name and the events. Okay, so
these are the mandatory parameters. So
the TSA server URL, URL of your TSCA
server, right? The project name, the
project root name of your TSCA project
where your test event which you are
trying to
execute and then the events. So
basically it is a JSON array of all the
test events which you want to execute.
Okay. And then the events config file
path path to the JSON file that contains
the event configuration. So there are
basically two ways of running this. One
you can directly pass the events and one
you can also pass a JSON file and then
the file path. Okay. Then there are some
optional uh parameters like the CA
certificate. Uh it is only required if
you're using HTTPS. Then the client ID,
client secret. Again these are based of
on HTTPS if your connection is
HTTPS. Uh client timeout. Okay. Then um
execution
environment the execution ID
um you can also put a polling interval
which means it will wait for some time
or you can uh request time out or
retries retry delay uh results file
name. So where do you want to save the
file name? Okay, this is by default
saved in the same folder but if you want
you can also save it in somewhere else.
uh you can define the folder and file
path for those results. You can also
deactivate the login logging right which
is done. Then the log folder path um and
all of these optional parameters which
you can pass apart from this but the
main parameters or mandatory parameters
are these four parameters.
Okay. So uh this is what we need to do.
Uh the first step is as I said we need
to download this execution client. I'll
be working on the Windows system because
we have already set up our Dex um and
also our Dex agent, our Dex server,
everything is on one Windows system,
right? So, uh here uh you need to make
sure that you are selected on the main
branch and then you need to go here into
the code and then you need to download
it as a zip.
Okay. So, do that. And once it's
downloaded, then I'm going to extract
this
here. Okay. And then I'm going to copy
this and I'm going to save it somewhere.
So, I've got this C execution folder
where I'm going to save this.
Okay. And I'm going to rename this to to
TSA execution client. Inside this you
will find that readme.md file and then
this is the execution client toka
execution client when it is a windows
powershell script.
Okay. So yep. So that's it about
downloading the execution client. Once
we have that right now let's go ahead
and start our
powershell. So here is the powershell
and the first step which we need to do
is set the execution policy. Okay. So by
default u this execution policy is uh
set to undefined in in your system and
it will not allow you to execute the
script. Okay. For that you need to uh
basically do this. So we need to set
execution policy and we need to set the
policy to bypass and the scope will be
local machine. Okay. So this is the
command you need to run now.
Okay. Um it will ask you whether you
want to change this execution policy and
there are some security risk but uh
that's fine. We want to execute this
script. Okay. So once this execution
policy is executed then we can run our
execution script. Okay. Now this is the
command uh which was there. Okay. So it
starts with this PowerShell script. It
calls this and then we give the
parameters. Okay. So this is the TSCA
server URL you can see. So localhost 80.
Now it could be anything depending on
your server address. Just uh take your
IP and uh paste it here with the port.
Okay. And then the events. Um so in the
event I just want to execute this one
event which is sample. You just need to
give the test event name. Then the
project name uh which is multi-user.
Okay. Now if I go back to my uh TSA
project, you will see this is the
multi-user project and then under test
events, I have got this sample test
event. I have created this uh it is uh
it has got a dex configuration which is
a dex uh which is a dex agent and then
it will execute this login script.
Okay. So this is how uh you can execute
it on the TSA execution client. So now
just copy this but first uh we need to
go to that particular folder where that
execution client is otherwise you will
get error that it is not executable.
Okay. So first uh we are going to go
here
right and then we are going to execute
that particular command. So let's copy
this and then come here
and okay and then
execute. So you will see that um it will
start
execution and uh it will successfully
encue the execution or the dex event. It
will start the execution. Okay.
and then it will complete the execution
and um it will store the results as
well. Okay. So you can see on my screen
uh the swag labs um screen has opened
and it is going to login into this that
was my test script and it is being
executed from the command line tool
which is toka execution client. Okay. So
the execution is now
complete and the same you can see here
um it has already executed this. Okay.
So this is the recent event which I have
executed right. So it it executed it
from the execution
client and then it will also store the
results as I said. Okay. So if you go
into the TSA execution client folder uh
you will see it has stored in the logs
that is the logs. Okay. So if you want
if there is any error you can go through
this uh logs uh to debug any particular
issue or um if you want to see the
results there is the result in XML file.
So I can open it with any particular
browser. Okay. It is not the best format
as you can see here but it tells you uh
so the test suit name uh the tests uh
how many failed how many passed uh the
time taken so all these details are here
okay so it it is XML format but uh you
know you can um always convert it into a
proper format or if you're using a CI/CD
client like genkins you can always uh do
the reporting using this XML file. Okay.
So this uh particular client is made for
your CI/CD pipelines so that you can
integrate it easily with any CI/CD
client, right? And then it is much
faster because it is not dependent on
your machine or any other uh
configuration. It is just running from a
command line tool like PowerShell,
right? And then uh if you have genkins
configured then you can easily call this
PowerShell script uh by just uh creating
a genkins build and then um calling this
PowerShell script just like how we have
done in our local. We'll be doing the
same thing in the
genkins. Now let's jump onto uh Genkins
and let's see how we can execute the
same thing not from the PowerShell but
from a CI/CD client like genkins. Okay.
So uh I am in my genkins you can see
here. So we need to create a new item
and let's name it
execution client
or okay and then create a freestyle
project here. Click on
okay and then you can fill the
description. All the other options are
really optional. Okay, because we will
not be using all of these options. The
main option here is the build steps.
Okay, and we need to add a build step
here. You can see there are different
types of commands which we can run here
and one of them is PowerShell. Now if
you're not able to see this option uh go
into your uh TSA plugins and then
download this particular plug-in called
PowerShell. Okay. And then you'll be
able to execute the PowerShell commands
here. So now uh we can execute this
PowerShell script here. Okay. And we are
going to enter this here. But before
that as you remember we need to go to a
particular directory. Right? So I'm
going to go to that particular directory
here where our execution client is
present. Right? So these are the two uh
lines of script which we want to execute
on this PowerShell. Right? And then uh
I'm going to save this and go back to my
dashboard. So this is the genkins build
which uh we are going to execute.
Okay. Now here I'm going to click on
build.
now and it will start the build right
away. Okay. So this is our build and
then uh we can go to the console output
and you can see the same logs are being
generated when we executed this on a
PowerShell um as a PowerShell script. It
was generating this logs and now you can
see it has opened u the demo website
where it is going to execute this
particular script. Right? So everything
remains the same but now uh we are able
to integrate our script right from a
CI/CD client like Jenkins. You can use
any CI/CD client as I said you just need
to make sure that in your build step you
are executing that PowerShell script
command. Okay. So that's all is required
in order to integrate your TSCA with any
particular CI/CD client.
Now um let's wait for uh this execution
to get over. Okay. And uh now you can
see it has finished as success. And you
can see it has also written the
execution results to this particular
file. Right. So see execution um and
results and this XML file. Okay. Now, as
I said, u if you're not able to find the
PowerShell option in your build step,
then uh you can go into your dashboard
and from there you can go to manage
genkins and go to
plugins and then you can go to installed
plugins. Okay, here uh I have already
installed PowerShell. You can see
PowerShell plug-in. If uh this is not
present for you, then go to available
plugins and then just type
powershell. Okay. So for me it will not
show because uh it's already present in
the installed plugins. But uh once you
type this PowerShell you will get that
plug-in and then just select it and then
install it. Okay. So that's all you need
to do. Okay. So this is how you can
install the PowerShell plug-in if you
want. Um now few other things which you
can do obviously is if you want to view
a particular report for this particular
build okay apart from the regular logs
which are present or the XML report
which is generated you can always
download the XML plug-in or any other
reporting plug-in which can basically
give you um a better report if you want
to see it in your genkins build. Okay.
So those things uh you can always do but
this is how you can use the TSCA
execution client to integrate your TSA
automation test suit with any particular
CI/CD client and then you can also
integrate this with the CI/CD pipeline
where your development changes can be
tested directly uh with your TSka test
cases. If your team is using the same uh
CI/CD client like genkins or anything
else that will be part of the pipeline
and once there is any code change then
there will be a trigger which will
execute uh your TSCA test cases
right. So this is all about uh CI/CD
integration um in TSCA with DEX uh and
EOS. So you can also set it up on your
uh TSCA machine similar to how I have
shown you.